<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A midnights trance wherin is discoursed of death, the nature of the soules, and estate of immortalitie. As it was written at the desire of a nobleman, by W.D.</title>
            <author>Drummond, William, 1585-1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12517</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7252.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117487</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852700</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852700</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177847</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12517)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177847)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1233:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A midnights trance wherin is discoursed of death, the nature of the soules, and estate of immortalitie. As it was written at the desire of a nobleman, by W.D.</title>
                  <author>Drummond, William, 1585-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 97, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Purslow, for Iohn Budge, and are to be sold at the signe of the Greene-Dragon in Paules Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W.D. = William Drummond.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 6182.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 6182 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Some leaves tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Death --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177847:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177847:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A MIDNIGHTS Trance: Wherin is diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of DEATH, the nature of SOVLES, and estate of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie.</p>
            <p>As it was Written at the deſire of a Nobleman, <hi>By</hi> W. D.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>George Purſlow,</hi> for <hi>Iohn Budge,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Greene-Dragon in <hi>Paules</hi> Church-yard. 1619.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:177847:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177847:2"/>
            <head>A MIDNIGHTS Trance, wherin is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of Death, The nature of Soules, and eſtate of Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hough it hath beene doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed if there be in the Soule of Man ſuch imperious and ſuperexcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Power, as that it can by the vehement and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177847:3"/>working of it, deliuer knowledge to another without bodily Organs, and by the only concepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and <hi>Ideas</hi> of it, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce reall effects, yet it hath beene euer and of all thought infallible &amp; moſt certaine, that it often (ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by outward inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or ſome ſecret motion of it ſelfe) is augure of its owne Misfortunes, and hath ſhadowes of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Dangers preſented vnto it, a while before they fall forth. Hence ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtrange apparitions and ſignes, true Viſions, Dreames moſt certaine,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177847:3"/>vncouth languiſhings and drowſineſſe, of which to ſeeke a reaſon, vnleſſe from the ſparkling of GOD in the Soule; or from the God-like ſparkles of the Soule, were to make <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> vnreaſonable, in reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of things tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her reach.</p>
            <p>Hauing often and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers times, when I had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen my ſelfe to reſt in the quiet ſolitarineſſe of the night, found my imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion troubled with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed feare, no, ſorrow, or Horror, which interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſleepe did confound my ſenſes, and rouſe mee
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:177847:4"/>vp all appalled, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported in a ſuddaine ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and ſad amazednes; of ſuch an vnaccuſtomed perturbation and name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe woe, not knowing, nor being able to imagine any apparant cauſe, carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away with the ſtreame of my (then doubting) thoghts, I was brought to aſcribe it to that ſecret fore-knowledg &amp; preſage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Power of the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke Mind; and to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret ſuch an agonie to bee to the Spirit, as a faintnes and vniuerſall wearineſſe is to the Body, a token of following ſickneſſe, or as
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:177847:4"/>the Earth-quakes are to great Cities, Harbingers of greater calamities, or as the roring of the Sea is, in a ſtil calme, a ſigne of ſome enſuing tempeſt.</p>
            <p>Hereupon, not thinking it ſtrange, if whatſoeuer is humane ſhould befall me, knowing how Prouidence abates griefe, and diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances croſſes, and that as we ſhould not deſpaire of euils, which may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen vs, wee ſhould not truſt too much in thoſe goods we enioy: I began to turne ouer in my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance all that could afflict miſerable mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177847:5"/>and to fore-caſt euery thing that with a Maske of Horror could ſhew it ſelfe to humane eyes, till in the end, as by vnities and points, Mathematicians are brought to great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and huge greatneſſe, after many fantaſticall gla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of mankinds ſorrow, and thoſe incumbrances which follow life, I was brought to thinke, and with amazement, on the laſt of humane euils, or (as one ſaid) the laſt of all dreadfull and terrible things, <hi>Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And why may wee not beleeue that the Soule
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177847:5"/>(though darkely) fore-ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and hauing ſecret in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence of that ſharpe diuorcement it is to haue from the body, ſhould be ouergrieued and ſurpriſed with an vncouth and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accuſtomed ſorrow? And at the firſt encounter exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining their neere vnion, long familiarity &amp; friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, with the great chang, paine, and vglines, which is apprehended to bee in <hi>Death,</hi> it ſhall not appeare to be without reaſon.</p>
            <p>They had their beeing together, parts they are of one reaſonable Creature, the hurting of the one, is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:177847:6"/>the enfeebling of the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the other, what deare contentments doth the Soule enioy by the ſenſes? They are the gates and windowes of its know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, the Organs of its delight; if it bee grieuous to an excellent Lutaniſt to bee long without a Lute, how much more muſt the want of ſo noble an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment bee painefull to the Soule? And if two Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims who haue wandred ſome few miles together, haue a hearts griefe when they part, what muſt the ſorrow be at the parting of two ſo louing friends, as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:177847:6"/>is the Soule and Body?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Death</hi> is the violent eſtranger of acquaintance, the eternall diuorcer of Marriage, the rauiſher of the Children from the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, the ſtealer of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, from the Children, the intomber of Fame, the only cauſe of forgetfulnes, by which men talk of them that are gon away, as of ſo many ſhadows, orageworn Stories. It is not ouercome by pride, made meeke by flattery, ſtaied by Time; Wiſedome ſaue this, can preuent &amp; help any thing: nor Youth, nor Vertue, nor Beauty, can make it relent and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177847:7"/>becom partial: It is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonles breaker off of al acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by this wee enioy no more the ſweet pleaſures of Earth, nor behold the ſtately Vault of Heauen, Sunne perpetually ſetteth, Stars neuer riſe vnto vs, all ſtrength by this is tane a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, all comlineſſe defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, Glory made ignoble, Honour turned into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt: This in an houre robbeth vs of, what with ſo great toyle and care in many yeeres, we haue hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped together: Succeſſions of Linages by this are cut ſhort; Kingdomes want Heires, and greateſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177847:7"/>States remaine Orphanes. By <hi>Death</hi> wee are exiled from this excellent City of the World, it is no more a world vnto vs, nor wee no more People vnto it.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Death,</hi> naturally is terrible &amp; to be abhorred, it cannot altogether be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, it being a priuatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Life, &amp; a not-being, &amp; eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry priuation being abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of nature, and euill of it ſelfe, yet I haue often thought that euen natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, to a minde by onely nature reſolued and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, it is more terrible in conceite then in verity, and at the firſt glance, then
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177847:8"/>when well looked vpon, &amp; that rather by the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our fantaſie, then by what is in it; and that the ſolemnities and ſhews of it, did adde much more vglineſſe vnto it, then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it hath: to auerre which concluſion, when I had gathered my aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed thoughts, I beganne thus with my ſelfe:</p>
            <p>If on the great Theater of this Earth, amongſt the numberleſſe number of Men, this condition were onely proper to thee and thine, then vndoubtedly, thou hadſt reaſon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine at ſo vniuſt and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177847:8"/>a Law: But ſince it is a neceſſity, from the which neuer an age by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt hath been exempted, and vnto which thoſe which bee, and ſo many as are to come, are thralled, it being as common, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the moſt vulgar thing to ſence, why ſhouldſt thou in thy peeuiſh oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition take ſo vneuitable and familiar a chance to heart? This is the broad path of mortalitie, our ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall home; behold what millions haue trod it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee, what multitudes ſhall after thee, with them who at that ſame inſtant
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177847:9"/>runne. In ſo vniuerſall a calamity (if DEATH bee one) priuate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints cannot bee heard, with ſo many royall Palaces, it is no loſſe to ſee thy poore cabin burne. Shall the Heauens ſtay their euer-roling wheeles (for what is the motion of them? but the motion of a ſwift, and euer-whirling wheele, which twineth forth, and againe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roleth our Life,) and hold ſtill time, to prolong thy miſerable dayes? As if they had nothing to doe els, but to ſerue thy humor. Thy Death is a peece of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177847:9"/>the order of this <hi>All,</hi> a part of the life of this World: for while the World is the World, ſome creatures muſt die, and other take Life. Eternall things are rayſed farre aboue this Spheare of generation &amp; corruption, where the firſt matter, like an euer-flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ebbing Sea, with diuerſe waues, but the ſame water remayneth; what is below in the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſality of the kind, not in it ſelfe doth abide, <hi>Man</hi> a long line of yeeres hath beene, this <hi>Man</hi> euery hundreth is ſwept away. This Center is the ſole Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177847:10"/>of <hi>Death,</hi> the Graue where euery thing that ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth life, muſt rotte, a Stage of change, only glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in the vnconſtancy, and manifold alterations of it, which though many, ſeeme yet to abide one, and being one, are yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer many. The neuer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing bodies of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Brethren turne one in another, the Earth changeth her countenance with the Seaſons, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times looking colde and naked, other times, hote &amp; flowrie; nay I cannot tell how, but euen the loweſt of thoſe heauenly bodies,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177847:10"/>that mother of Moneths, and Lady of Seas and moyſture, as if ſhee were a mirror of our conſtant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy, by her too great neareneſſe vnto vs ſeemeth to participate of our changes, neuer ſeeing vs twice with that ſame face, whiles appearing dark, now pale, ſometimes againe ſhining vnto vs. Death no leſſe then Life, doth here act a part, the taking away of what is old, being the making of a way for what is yong. Which ſince it is ſo, and muſt of neceſſity bee ſo, thou muſt learne to will, that which
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:177847:11"/>he wills, whoſe very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling giueth beeing to all that it wills, and rather to reuerence the ord'rer, then repine at the order, for we be borne not to giue lawes to God, and his Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Nature, but to obey thoſe Lawes which they haue giuen.</p>
            <p>If thou doſt complaine that there ſhall be a Time, in the which thou ſhalt not be, why doſt thou not too regreat that there was a Time, in the which thou waſt not? And ſo, that thou art not as old as that enlifening Planet of Time? For not to haue
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:177847:11"/>been a thouſand yeere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this moment, is as much to bee deplored, as not to be a thouſand after it. We know what Death is by the thought of that Time, and eſtate of our ſelues, which was ere wee were. Death is not to bee, that will be after vs, which long lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ere we were, was. Our Nephewes haue that ſame reaſon to vex them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, that they were not young men in our dayes, which wee haue to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine that we ſhall not be old in theirs; they who fore-went vs, did make place vnto vs: and ſhall we
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:177847:12"/>grieue to leaue a roome to them who come after vs? The Violets haue their time, though they liue not in the cold Winter, and the Gilly-flowers keepe their ſeaſon, though they ſpread not their leaues in the Spring.</p>
            <p>Empires, States, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, haue by the doom of the ſupreame Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence their fatall periods, great Cities lie ſadly buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their duſt, Arts and Sciences haue not onely their eclipſes, but their waynings and deaths, the gaſtly Wonders of the World rayſed by the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:177847:12"/>of ages are ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, the excellent Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricke of this Vniuerſe it ſelfe ſhall one day ſuffer ruine, or a change like a ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, and poore Earth-lings thus to be handled, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain. Seek now the <hi>Aſſyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, Median,</hi> &amp; <hi>Perſian</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires: where is the poſterity of that great <hi>Macedonian?</hi> And the terror of this Earth the <hi>Romane Caeſars?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But is this life ſo great a good, that the loſſe of it ſhold be ſo deare vnto ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? If it be? the meaneſt crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of nature thus be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, for they liue no leſs the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he: if it be ſo? how is it eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177847:13"/>by man himſelfe at ſo ſmal a rate? that for ſo ſmal gaine, nay, a light word, he wil not ſtand to loſe it? what excellency is there in it, for the which Man ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire it perpetually, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pine to return to his great Grand-mother Duſt? Of what worth are the labors and actions of it, that the interruption and leauing off of them ſhould bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayled? Is not the entring into life weakeneſſe? The continuing ſorrow? Man in the one is expoſed to all the iniuries of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and like a condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned treſpaſſer (as if it were
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:177847:13"/>a fault to com to the light) no ſooner born, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bound and manacled; in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, like a Ball hee is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly toſſed in the Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſ-court of this VVorld: VVhen hee is in the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian of his glory, there miſtereth nothing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy him, but to let him fall his owne hight, a reflex of the Sun, a blaſt of wind, nay, the glance of an Eye is ſufficient to kill him.</p>
            <p>His Body is but a Maſſe of diſcording humors boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led together by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring vertues of the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, which though agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for a time, yet can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:177847:14"/>be made vniforme and brought to a iuſt propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. To what ſickneſſe is it ſubiect vnto, beyond thoſe of the other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? no part of it beeing which is not particularly infected and afflicted by ſome one, nay euery part of it with many; ſo that not without reaſon, the life of diuers of the meaneſt creatures of Nature hath beene preferred (by the moſt wiſe) to the naturall life of Man. And wee ſhould rather be broght in a maze, how ſo fragila mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhould ſo long endure, then how ſo ſoone decay.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:177847:14"/>
            <p>Are the actions of the moſt part of men any thing different from thoſe labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious exerciſes of Spiders, that lye in ambuſh to pray on the ſimpler, and euiſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate themſelues many dais for the weauing of a fraile web, which when finiſhed with great toyle, a blaſt of wind carrieth away both the Worke and the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker? Or are they not ſuch indeed as bee the toyes of little Children? Or to hold them at their higheſt rate, as is ſome earneſt game at Cheſſe? Euery day we riſe and lye down, apparell and diſapparell
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:177847:15"/>our ſelues, weary our Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and refreſh them, which is a circle of idle trauels; ſometime wee are in a chaſe after a fading beauty; now wee ſeeke to enlarge our bounds, aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment our Treaſure, fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding poorely to purchaſe what wee muſt leaue (per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) to a foole, or (which is not much better) a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digall heire: raiſed again with the wind of Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wee court that idle name of Honor, not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that men in glaſſy places are but tortured ghoſts, wandring in gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Fetters, and gliſtring
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:177847:15"/>Priſons, hauing <hi>feare</hi> and <hi>danger</hi> their vnſeparable executioners, in the midſt of multitudes rather gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded then regarded.</p>
            <p>Thoſe whom inward Melancholly hath made weary of the Worlds eye, who haue withdrawne themſelues fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the courſe of earthly affaires, by thoughts curious, ſad re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grets, idle contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, liue a life farre worſe then others, their wit bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing too quicke to giue them a true taſte of woe, while thoſe of a more ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and ſimple conceit, haue want of knowledge
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:177847:16"/>and ignorance of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelus, for a remedy againſt euery other euill. What <hi>Camelion,</hi> what <hi>Euripe,</hi> what Moone doth change ſo oft as man? Hee ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not the ſame perſon in one and the ſame Day, by reaſon of his ſubiection to his priuate Paſſions.</p>
            <p>Young, wee ſcorne our childiſh conceits, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding deeper in yeeres (for yeres are a Sea into which we wade vntill we drown) we eſteeme our Youth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy, Folly, Raſhnes: Old, wee begin to pity our ſelues, plaining, becauſe we are changed, that the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:177847:16"/>World is changed: Like them in a Shippe, which when it is they that launch fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſhore, are brought to beleeue that the ſhore doth flie from them. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we are freed of euill in our owne eſtate, wee begin to grudge and vex our ſelues at the happineſſe and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes of others, wee are fraught, wee care for what is preſent, with ſadnes for what is by-paſt, with feare for that which is to come, nay, for that which will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer come; we deeme that pitty, which is but weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and plunge our ſelues in the deepeſt gulfes of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:177847:17"/>one day ſtill laying vp ſtrife of griefe for the next. The Aire, the Sea, the Fire, the Beaſts be cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell executioners of Man, yet Beaſts, Fire, Sea, and Ayre, bee pitifull to Man, in reſpect of Man; for, mo men are deſtroied by men, then by them all.</p>
            <p>What wrongs, ſcornes, contumelies, priſons, poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, torments, receiueth man of man? What en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines and new workes of death are daylie found forth by man againſt man? What Lawes to thrall his liberty? Fantaſies and ſcar-crowes to inueigle his
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:177847:17"/>
               <hi>reaſon?</hi> Amongſt the Beaſtes, is there any hath ſo ſeruile a lot in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers behalfe as man? yet neither is content, nor hee who raigneth, nor he who ſerueth.</p>
            <p>The halfe of our Life is ſpent in ſleepe, which (ſith it is a releaſe of care, the balme of woe, and indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent arbiter vnto all) muſt be the beſt, and yet is but the ſhadow of Death: and who would not rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuffer the Slings, and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows of outragious For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, the whips and ſcorns of time, the oppreſſors wrongs, the proud mans
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:177847:18"/>contumelies, ſleepe euer (that is, dye) and end the Heart-ake, and the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand naturall Shocks, that fleſh is heire to? Our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe heere, ſeemeth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the wanting of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, and being free of croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, then in the enioying of any great good. What hath the braueſt of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals to glory in? Is it great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? Who can be great on ſo ſmall a round as this Earth? and bounded with ſo ſhort a courſe of Time? How like is that to caſtles, or imaginary Cities, buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Skie, of chance-meeting Clouds? Or to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:177847:18"/>Giants modelled (for a ſport) of Snow, which at the hotter lookes of the Sunne do melt away? ſuch an impetuous viciſſitude ſo towſeth the eſtates of this World. Is it know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge? But wee haue not yet attained a perfect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt floure, and why, the graſſe ſhould rather bee greene, then red, the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of fire is quite put out the Ayre is but water rari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, ſome affirme there is another world of men and creatures, with Cities, and Towers in the Moone, the Sunne is loſt, for it is
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:177847:19"/>but a cleft in the lower Heauens, through which the light of the higheſt ſhines: What is all we know, compared with what wee know not? It is (perhaps) artificiall cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: how many curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties be framed by the leaſt creatures of Nature, vnto which, the induſtry of the moſt curious Artizans doth not attaine? Is it Riches? What are they but ſnares of Liberty, bands to ſuch as haue them, poſſeſſing, rather then poſſeſſed: Metalls which <hi>Nature</hi> hath hidde (foreſeeing the great euill
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:177847:19"/>they ſhould occaſion) and the only opinion of Men, hath brought in eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? When wee haue gathered the greateſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundance, wee our ſelues can enioy no more there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, then ſo much as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to one man, Rich and great men doe their buſineſſe by others, the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer doe them themſelues. Will ſome talke of our pleaſures? It is not (though in the fables) told out of purpoſe, that <hi>Pleaſure</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called in haſte from Earth to Heauen, did here forget her apparell, which <hi>Sorrow</hi> hauing thereafter
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:177847:20"/>found (to deceiue the World) attired her ſelfe with; and if wee ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the truth of moſt of our ioyes, we muſt ſay that they are but diſguiſed Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, the drammes of our honey, are loſt in pounds of Gall, Remorſe neuer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſueth our beſt Delights. Will ſome Ladies vaunt of their Beauties? That is but skinne-deepe, of two ſenſes onely knowne, ſhort euen of Marble Statues and Pictures, dangerous to the beholder, and hurt. full to the poſſeſſor, an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to Chaſtity, a thing made to delight others,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:177847:20"/>and not thoſe who haue it, a ſuperficiall luſtre hiding Bones and the Braines, things fearefull to bee loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vpon; growth of yeres doth take it away, or ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or ſorrow preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them; our ſtrength, matched with that of the vnreaſonable creatures, is but weakeneſſe.</p>
            <p>If Death be good, why ſhould it be feared? And if it bee the worke of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, how ſhall it not bee good? And how ſhall it not bee of Nature? Sith what is naturally generate, is ſubiect to corruption, for ſuch a compoſition
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:177847:21"/>cannot euer endure, but muſt of neceſſity diſſolue. Againe, how is not <hi>Death</hi> good, fith it is the thaw of all thoſe miſeries which the froſt of life bindeth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether? In two or three ages (without <hi>Death</hi>) what an vnpleaſant ſpectacle were the moſt flouriſhing Cities in the World? For what ſhould there bee to be ſeene in them, ſaue bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies languiſhing, and courbing againe into the Earth? Pale diſfigured fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Skelitones in ſtead of Men? And what were there to bee heard, but the regrets of the yong, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:177847:21"/>Plaints of the aged, with the pittifull cries of ſicke and pining perſons? there is almoſt no infirmity worſe then age.</p>
            <p>If there bee any euill in Death, it would appeare to bee for that paine and torment, which we appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend to ariſe of the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of thoſe ſtraight ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds which keep the Soule and Bodie together, which (ſince it is not without great wreſtling and moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) ſeemes to proue it ſelfe vehement and moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme. The ſences are the onely cauſe of paine, but before that laſt effect
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:177847:22"/>traries, that the worſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Bodies feele paine leaſt, and by this reaſon all ſicke perſons ſhould not much feele paine, for if they were not euill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed they would not bee ſicke.</p>
            <p>That the ſight, hearing, ſmelling, taſte, leaue vs without paine, and vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, wee know moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely, and why ſhould wee not beleeue the ſame of the feeling? That which is capable of feeling is the vitall Spirits, which in a man of good health are ſpred &amp; extended through the whole Body: And
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:177847:22"/>hence is it, that the whole body is capable of paine; but in ſicke men wee ſee that by degrees thoſe parts which are moſt remoued from the heart, remaine cold, and being denuded of naturall heate, all the pain that they feele, is that they can feele no paine: now as before the ſicke be aware, the vitall Spirits re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire themſelues from the whole extenſion of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, to aſſiſt the heart, (like diſtreſſed Citizens, which finding their wals battred run to defend their Citta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dell) ſo do they abandon the heart without any ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:177847:23"/>touch, as the flame withdrawes it ſelfe from the wicke, the Oyle fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. As to thoſe ſhrink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing motions and conuulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ſinewes and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, which appeare to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe great paine, let one repreſent to himſelfe the ſtrings of a high-tuned Lute, which being cracked retire to their naturall winding, or a piece of Ice which without any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward violence cracks at a Thaw: no other waies do the ſinewes of the body, finding themſelues ſlacke and vnbended from the Braine, and that their won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:177847:23"/>labours and functions do ceaſe, ſtruggle and ſeeme to ſtirre themſelues without any paine or ſence.</p>
            <p>Now, although Death were an extreme paine, ſith it is in an inſtant, what can it bee? Why ſhould wee feare it? For while we are, it commeth not, and it being come, wee are no more. Nay, though it were moſt painefull, long continuing, and terrible vgly, why ſhould we feare it? Since feare is a fooliſh paſſion but where it may preſerue, but it cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue vs from death. That
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:177847:24"/>is euer terrible, which is vnknown: ſo do little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren feare to goe in the darke, and their feare is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed with tales.</p>
            <p>But that (perhaps) which doth bring thee moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, is to leaue this pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Sceane of the World in the Spring, and moſt delicious ſeaſon of thy yeeres; for, though to die be vſual, to die young may appeare extraordinary. If the preſent fruition of theſ things be fooliſh, what can a long continuance of them be? Poore and ſtrang <hi>Halcyon,</hi> why wouldeſt thou longer neſtle amidſt
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:177847:24"/>theſe inconſtant waues? haſt thou not already ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred enough of this world, but thou muſt yet endure more? But count thy yeres which are now () &amp; thou ſhalt find, that whereas ten haue ouer-liued thee, thouſands haue not attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this age. One yeere is ſufficient to behold all the magnificence of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nay euen one day and night, for more is but the ſame brought againe.</p>
            <p>This Sun, that Moone, thoſe Starres, the diſponſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Spring, Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Autumne, Winter, is that very ſame which the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:177847:25"/>Golden age did ſee. They which haue the longeſt time lent them to liue in, haue almoſt nothing of it at all, ſetting it eyther by that which is paſt, when they were not, or by that which is to come: Why ſhouldſt thou then regard, whether thy dayes be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny or few; which when prolonged to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, muſt proue (paraleld with Eternitie) as a Teare is to the Ocean? It is hope of long Life, that maketh life ſeeme ſhort. Who will weigh, &amp; aduiſedly weigh the inconſtancy of humane affaires, with the back-blows
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:177847:25"/>of Fortune, ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer lament to die yong. Who knoweth what diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſters might haue befallen him, who dieth yong, if hee had liued to been old? Hauen taketh them whom it loueth, from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers before they doe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach; pure and (if wee may ſay ſo) virgin Soules carrie their bodies with great anguiſh, and delight not to abide long in them, being euer burnt with a deſire to returne to the place of their reſt; and to be relieued of fleſhly vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanlyneſſe, that which may fall forth euery houre,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:177847:26"/>cannot fall out of time: life is a iourney in a duſtie way, the furtheſt home is <hi>Death,</hi> in this, ſome goe more heauily burthened then others, ſwift &amp; actiue Pilgrimes come to the end of it in the morning, or at Noone: which ſlow-paced wretches, clogged with the fragmentall rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh of this world, ſcarce with great trauell, crawle vnto at midnight. Dayes are not to be numbred af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the number of them; but after their goodneſſe, the greatnes of a Spheare, addeth nothing to the roundneſſe of it, but a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:177847:26"/>circle is as round as the moſt ample; that Muſician is not moſt praiſe-worthie, who hath longeſt played, but he in meaſur'd accents who hath made ſweeteſt melodie; to liue long, hath often beene a let to liue well. Let it ſuffice that thou haſt liued to this time, and (after the courſe of this world) not for nought, thou haſt had ſome ſmiles of Fortune, fauors of the worthieſt, ſome friends, &amp; thou haſt neuer beene disfauoured of the Heauen.</p>
            <p>Yet it is almoſt impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that thou canſt want a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:177847:27"/>deſire to liue, and wiſheſt not thy dayes a while con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, though not for life it ſelfe, at leaſt that thou mayſt leue to after-times a monument, that once thou waſt; for ſince it is denied vs to liue long, (ſaid one) let vs leaue ſome wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy remembrance of our once here being, and thus extend this ſpanne of Life ſo farre as is poſſible. O poore Ambition! to what I pray thee canſt thou concreded it? Arches and ſtately Temples, which one age doth rayſe, doth not another raze? Tombs and adopted pillers lie bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:177847:27"/>with them which were in them buried; hath not auarice defaced that, which Deuotion did make glorious? All that the hand of Man can make, is eyther ouerturned by the hand of Man, or at length by very ſtanding and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing conſumed; as if there were a ſecret oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Fate, to controle al our induſtrie. Poſſeſſions are not enduring, children loſe their Names, fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies raiſed on the higheſt top of wealth and Honor (like thoſe which are not yet born) leauing off to be, ſo doth Heauen confound
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:177847:28"/>what we labor with Art to diſtinguiſh. That renowne by Papers, which is though to make men glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and which neereſt doth approach the Life of thoſe eternall Bodies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, how ſlender it is, the very word of paper doth import; and what is it when obtained, but a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of words which comming Worlds may ſcorne? How many mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions neuer heare the names of the moſt famous Writers? And amongſt them to whom they are knowne, how few turne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their pages? And of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:177847:28"/>ſuch as doe, how many ſport at their conceits, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the verity for a Fable, and oft a Fable for Veritie, or (as wee doe pleaſants) vſing all for recreation? Then the ariſing of more famous doth obſcure and darken the glory of the former, being eſteemed as Garments worne out of faſhion. Now when thou haſt obtained what praiſe thou couldſt deſire, it is but an Eccho, a meere ſound, a cloud of Ayre; which ſeene a farre, did appeare ſomething, but approached, is found nought; a thing imaginary
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:177847:29"/>depending on the opinion of other Men; for it is hard to diſtinguiſh vertue and fortune, the moſt vicious (if proſperous) haue euer beene prayſed, the moſt vertuous (if vnproſperous) haue ſtill beene deſpiſed. Applauſe obtained whilſt thou liueſt, hath euer enuy following it, and is brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, like that <hi>Syracuſians</hi> Spheare of Glaſſe; and borne after thy Death, it may as well be aſcribed to ſome of them that were in the <hi>Troian</hi> Horſe, or to ſuch as are yet to be borne an hundreth yeeres hereafter, as to thee who no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:177847:29"/>knows, and is of all vnknown: What can it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile thee to bee talked of whilſt thou art not? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider in what bounds our Fame is confined: This Globe which ſeemeth large to vs, in reſpect of the Vniuerſe, is leſſe then little, how much thereof is coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with Waters, how much not at al diſcouered? How much deſart and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate And how many thouſand thouſands are they which ſhare the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent amongſt them? &amp; all this is but a point, &amp; in compariſon nothing to that wide wide canopie
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:177847:30"/>of Heauen. For the Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon that bounds our ſight, bindeth the Heauen as in two halfs, which it could not doe if the Earth had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny quantity compared to it. More, if it were not as a point, the Starres could not ſtill appeare to vs of a like greatneſſe in reſpect of their diurnall motion: for where the Earth rayſed it ſelfe in Mountaines (wee being more neere to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen) they would appeare more great, and where it were humbled in vallies (we being farther diſtant) they would ſeeme vnto vs leſſe.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:177847:30"/>
            <p>But on all ſides the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen beeing equally diſtant from the earth, of neceſſity wee muſt auouch it to bee but a point. Well did one compare it to an Ant-hill, and men (the Inhabitants) to ſo many Piſmires in the toyle and variety of their diuerſified ſtudies. But let it be granted that Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Fame is ſome great matter, and can reach Heauen it ſelfe, ſince it is often buried with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored, and endureth ſo ſhort a time, what great good can it haue in it? How is not Glory tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, ſince it increaſeth with
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:177847:31"/>Time? Then imagine me (for what cannot imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion reach vnto?) one could bee famous in all times to come, &amp; through the whole World preſen, t yet he ſhall be for euer ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, and vncouth to thoſe mighty ones, who were only heretofore famous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt <hi>Aſsyrians, Perſians, Greekes,</hi> and <hi>Romanes.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, the vaine affectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Man</hi> is ſo ſuppreſſed, that though his workes do abide, the worker is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne: the huge <hi>Aegyptt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Pyramides</hi> though they haue wraſtled with time, and worne vpon the vaſt
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:177847:31"/>of dayes, yet their builders be no more knowne, then it is known by what ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge Earth-quakes and Deluges Iles were diuided from the continent, and Hils burſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth of the low Vallies. Dayes, Moneths, and yeres runne away, and only ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuion remaines; of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ages paſt wee may well figure to our ſelues ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but can affirme little certainty.</p>
            <p>But, Oh my Soule, what ailes thee to be thus back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and fearefull at the remembrance of <hi>Death?</hi> ſith it doth not reach thee, more then darkneſſe doth
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:177847:32"/>thoſe eternall Lampes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue: rowſe thy ſelfe for ſhame, why ſhouldſt thou feare to bee without a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſince thy Maker and thoſe ſpirituall and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celeſtiall Inhabitants haue no Bodies? Haſt thou e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſeen any Priſoner who when the Iayle-gates were broken vp and hee enfran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſed and ſet looſe, would rather plaine and ſit ſtill on his fetters, then ſeeke his freedome? If thou right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thinke on thy ſelf thou haſt no cauſe of ſorrow: for, if there bee any reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance in what is finite of that which is infinite, if
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:177847:32"/>thou bee not an Image, thou art a ſhadow of that eternall <hi>Trinitie,</hi> in thy three eſſential Powers, Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding Will, Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, which though three, are in thee but one: and yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding one bee diſtinctly three. But in no thing more commeſt thou neere that <hi>Soueraigne good</hi> then in thy Immortality, which who ſeeke to improue, by that ſame it proue, like them who arguing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to bee vnreaſonable, by the very arguing ſhew that they haue ſome. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this viſible world is comparable to thee,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:177847:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:177847:33"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:177847:34"/>thou art ſo wonderfull a beauty, and beautifull a Wonder, that if but once thou couldſt be gazed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by bodily eyes, euery heart would be inflamed with thy loue, &amp; eleuated fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their groueling earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſires. What God is in the World, thou art in the body, abiding on the Earth, thou meaſureſt the Heauen, thou makeſt the Seas and VVinds to ſerue thee, thou many things foreknoweſt before they fall forth, thou art not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with the ſight of all, within the ſpacious bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of this large Cloiſter of
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:177847:34"/>the VVorld, vntill thou rayſe thy ſelfe to the happy contemplation of that firſt illuminating intelligence, tranſcending time, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen reaching Eternity it ſelfe, into which thou art tranſformed: for by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing, thou (beyond all other things) art made that which thou receiueſt. By thy three faculties, thou participateſt with the three parts of Time; by Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with that which hath paſſed, by Vnderſtanding with that which is preſent, &amp; by VVil with that which is to come.</p>
            <p>Man by thee is that <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:177847:35"/>of celeſtiall and terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriall things, without whom the vniuerſall frame and great Fabrick of this world would remaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect. Thou only at once art capable of contraries, thou knoweſt thy ſelfe an immediat maſter peece of that eternall artizan, &amp; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeſt thee ſo ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, abſolute, and diuerſe an eſſence from thy Body, that thou diſpoſeſt of it, as it pleaſeth thee: for there is no paſſion in thee ſo weake which maſtereth not the feare of leauing it. The more thou knoweſt, the more apt thou art to know,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:177847:35"/>not remayning enfabled by thine object as ſenſe by obiects ſenſible. Thou ſhouldſt bee ſo farre from abhorring this ſeparation, that it ſhould be the firſt of thy deſires, it being thy perfection. Thou art here but as in an infected and vncleane Inne, or a liuing Tombe, oppreſſed with cares, ſuppreſſed with ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance: Moſt of thy knowledge commeth by thy fine intelligencers of ſence, which (being often deceiued) deceiue thee: ſmall things ſeeme here great vnto thee, and great things ſmall: Folly Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:177847:36"/>and Wit Folly: freed of thy fleſhly care thou ſhalt rightly know thy ſelfe, and haue perfect fruition of that full and fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling happineſſe, which is God himſelfe. God and happineſſe are one, for if God haue not happineſſe, hee is not God, becauſe happineſſe is the higheſt and ſoueraigneſt good: then if God haue happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, it cannot be a thing different from him, for if there were any thing diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from him in him, hee ſhould be an eſſence com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and not ſimple. More, what is different in
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:177847:36"/>any thing, is eyther an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, or a part of it ſelfe; in God, happineſſe cannot be an accident, becauſe he is not ſubiect to any acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; if it were a part of him (ſince the part is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the whole) wee ſhould be forced to grant that ſomething was before God. Bedded and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in theſe earthly <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dures,</hi> thou canſt not come neer that ſoueraigne good, nor haue ſo much notice of him, as the Owle hath of the Sun. Thinke then by <hi>Death</hi> that thy ſhel is broke &amp; thou then but eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: VVhy ſhouldſt thoube
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:177847:37"/>feare-ſtroken, and brought vnder for the parting with this mortall Bride, thy Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy? Sith it is but for a time, and ſuch a time as ſhe ſhall not care for, nor feele any thing in, nor thou haue need of her, nay, ſince thou ſhalt receiue her a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine more goodly and beautifull, then when thou leftſt her? Being made like vnto that <hi>Indian</hi> Chriſtall, which after ſome reuoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of ages is turned into pureſt Diamonds.</p>
            <p>If the Soule be the form of the Body, and the forme ſeparated from the matter of it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not euer remain, but
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:177847:37"/>hath a natural appetite and deſire to bee vnited there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, what can let and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this deſire, but that one time or other it be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, and haue the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected end, adioyning it ſelfe to the body? No vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent thing can bee euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, the abiding of the Soule without the body being violent, cannot bee euerlaſting. How is not ſuch a beeing not violent, ſince as in a ſtranger place the faculties of it (which neuer leaue it) are not due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exerciſed?: this is not contradictory to Nature, much leſſe impoſſible to God.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:177847:38"/>
            <p>If the body ſhall not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, how can the only and ſoueraigne Good bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly and infinitely good? For how ſhall hee be Iuſt? Nay, haue ſo much iuſtice as a man, if hee ſuffer the euill and vicious to haue a more proſperous and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py life then the followers of Vertue? Which ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily vſeth to fall forth in this life: for the moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked are lords and gods of this earth, as if it had been made only for them, and the vertuous are but their enuaſſaled ſlaues, beeing ſubiect to all diſhonors, ſhames, wrongs, miſerie.
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:177847:38"/>Sith then he is moſt good, moſt iuſt, of neceſſity there muſt be appointed by him another time, and another place of retribution, in the place of retribution, in the which there ſhall bee a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for liuing well, and a puniſhment for doing euil, with a life in the which both ſhall haue their due; and not in their Soules on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: for, ſith both the parts of man did act a part in the right or wrong, it is reaſon they both be arraigned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that High Iuſtice, to receiue their owne. For man is not a Soule onely, but a Soule and Body, to which either guerdon or
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:177847:39"/>puniſhment is due.</p>
            <p>This ſeemeth to bee the voice of Nature in almoſt all the Religions of the World, this is that vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall teſtimony charactered in the minds of the moſt barbarous and ſauage peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; for all haue had a blind ayming at ages to come, and a miſtie diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of another life, all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealing to one generall Iudgement Throne. To what elſe could ſerue ſo many expiations, ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Prayers, ſolemnities and ceremonies? To what ſuch ſumptuous Temples, and ſuch care of the dead?
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:177847:39"/>To what all Religion? If not to ſhew that they did looke for a more excellent eſtate of liuing after the ſhort courſe of this was out-runne: and who doth deny it, muſt deny that that there is a God, a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, and not beleeue that there is a World or Creatures, and that hee himſelfe is not what hee is.</p>
            <p>But it is not of <hi>Death</hi> (perhaps) that wee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, but of Time, which vſing againſt vs (as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all fragil and caduke things) his adamantine
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:177847:40"/>Lawes, altereth the conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of our Bodies, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nummes our ſences, and the Organes of our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, of which euils <hi>Death</hi> relieueth vs: So that if we could be tranſported (oh happy Colonie!) to a place where there were no time, it were our only good, and the accompliſhment of all our wiſhes. <hi>Death</hi> maketh this tranſplantation, for the laſt inſtant of corruption, or leauing off of a thing to be what it was, is the firſt of generation or being of that which ſucceedeth; Death then beeing the end of this miſerable mortall
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:177847:40"/>life, of neceſſity muſt bee the firſt beginning of that other eternall; and ſo with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon of a vertuous Soule is it either feared or complained on.</p>
            <p>As thoſe Images were figured in my Mind, (the morning-Star now almoſt ariſing in the Eaſt) I found my thoughts to become calme and appeaſed, and not long after my ſences one by one forgetting their vſes, began to giue themſelues ouer to reſt, leauing mee in a ſtill and quiet ſleepe, if ſleep it may be called, where the Mind
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:177847:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:177847:41"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:177847:42"/>awaking is carried with free wings fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out fleſhly bondage? For, heauy lids had no ſooner couered their lights, when I thoght (nay ſure) I was where I might diſcerne all in this great <hi>All,</hi> the large compas of the rowling Circles, the brightneſſe and continuall dances of the twinkling Starres, which (through their diſtance) here below cannot bee perceiued, the ſiluer countenance of the ſilent Moone ſhining by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers light, the hanging of the Earth (as enuironed with a Chriſtall girdle) the Sunne enthronized in the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:177847:42"/>midſt of the Planets, Eye of the Heauens, Gemme of this goodly Ring the World. But whilſt with wonder and amazement I gazed on thoſe celeſtiall twinnes, and the burning Lamps of that glorious Temple, (like ſome poore Countrey-man brought from his ſolitary Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and flocks to behold the magnificence of ſome ſtately City) there was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to my ſight a Man as in the ſpring of his yeres, with that ſelfeſame grace, comely feature, and maieſticke looke, which the late ( <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> ) was wont
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:177847:43"/>to haue: on whom I had no ſooner ſet mine eye, when (like one thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroken) I became all aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. But hee with a mild demeanour appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and voice ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all humane ſweete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe appeared (mee thought) to ſay:</p>
            <p>What is it doth thus torture thee? is it the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of <hi>Death,</hi> the end of all Sorrow and entrie to theſe happy places? is thy fortune below on that dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened Globe (that ſcarce through the littleneſſe of it heere appeares) ſo great,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:177847:43"/>that thou art heart-broken and deiected for the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of it? what if thou hadſt left behind thee a ( <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> ) ſo glorious to the world (yet but a mote of duſt encircled with a Pond) as that of mine? ſo louing Parents? ſuch great Hopes? theſe had beene apparant occaſions of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grate, and but apparant. Doſt thou thinke that thou leaueſt life too ſoone? Death is beſt yong, things faire and excellent are of leaſt endurance, the Roſe which is the flowre of flowers, that ſame day that ſees it ſpred in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:177847:44"/>ſees it fade at eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and loſe the leaues, the Spring-time the moſt amiable Seaſon of the yeere is the Shorteſt. Who liueth well, liueth long, thoſe whom GOD loueth beſt, are ſoone re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued of mortall miſeries.</p>
            <p>Let not man eſteeme his eſtate, after his earthly being, which is but a Dreame, though hee bee borne on the earth, hee is not borne for the earth, more then the embrion for the Mothers wombe: it plaineth to bee relieued of its Bands, and to come
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:177847:44"/>to the light of this world, and Man mourneth to bee looſed from the Chaines with which he is fettered in that inchanted valley of vanities, it nothing know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth whither it is to goe, nor ought of the beauty of the ſenſible world, and the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible workes of God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe men of the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence of this intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all world aboue, vnto which (as by a Mid-wife) they are directed by <hi>Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fooles, who thinke that this excellent and admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Frame, ſo wel ordered, ſo rightly gouerned, ſo
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:177847:45"/>wonderfully faire, was by that ſupreme Wiſedome made, that all things in a circulary courſe ſhould be and not bee, ariſe and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue, and thus continue, as if they were ſo many Shadowes cauſed by the incountring of the Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or Celeſtiall bodies, chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging only their faſhion and ſhape; or were dreames which for a morning haue their being in the braine: No, no, the eternall Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome hath made man an excellent creature, though hee faine would vnmake himſelfe and turne againe to nothing, though hee
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:177847:45"/>ſeeke his happineſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the vnreaſonable creatures hee hath placed aboue.</p>
            <p>When ſome Prince or great King on the earth hath builded any ſtately City, the worke being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, they were wont to ſet their Image in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of it, to be gazed vpon and admired; No other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe hath the Soueraine of this <hi>All,</hi> (the fabricke of it done) placed Man, (made to his own Image) in the midſt of this admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable City. God contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all in him as the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of al, Man contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:177847:46"/>al in him as the midſt of all, inferior things be in man more nobly then they exiſt, ſuperior things more baſely, celeſtiall things fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour him, earthly things are vaſſaled vnto him, hee is the band of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it poſſible but that both of them haue peace with him, if he haue peace with him who made the couenant betweene them and him.</p>
            <p>Hee was made, that hee might know the infinite goodneſſe, power, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of him who made him, and knowing loue, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing enioy him, and to
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:177847:46"/>hold the Earth of him as of his Lord Paramount.</p>
            <p>How can it bee thought that God ſhould giue ſo long life to Trees, Beaſts, and the Birds of the Ayre, being Creatures inferior to Man, which haue leſſe vſe of it, and denie it to him, vnleſſe hee had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared another manner of liuing for him in a place more excellent?</p>
            <p>But O God! (ſaid I) had it not been better that for the good of his natiue Countrey ſo ( <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> ) had yet liued? How long will ye (replied he) like the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:177847:47"/>Ants thinke there bee no fayrer palaces then their hills, and like poreblinde Moles there is no greater light, then that little which they ſhunne? As if the maſter of a Campe knew when to remoue a Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, and hee who placeth Man on this Earth, did not know how long he had neede of him? Euery one commeth here to act his part of this Tragicomedie called Life, which done, the Curtaine is drawne, and he remouing from the Stage is ſaid to die.</p>
            <p>Moſt ( <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> ) then (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:177847:47"/>I) <hi>Death</hi> is not ſuch an euill and paine, as it is of the vulgar eſteemed? <hi>Death</hi> (ſaid he) nor paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is nor euill of it ſelfe, except in contemplation of the cauſe of it, being as indifferent as birth: Yet it cannot be denied, but that the vncouthneſſe of it, with the wrong apprehenſion of what is vnknowne in it is noyſome. But the Soule ſuſtained by its Maker, prepared and calmely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired in it ſelfe, doth finde that <hi>Death</hi> (ſince it is in a moment of time) is but a ſhort, nay ſweete ſigh, and is not worthy the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:177847:48"/>compared with the ſmalleſt dramme of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite happineſſe of this place.</p>
            <p>Here is the Palace roy all of the Almighty King, in which the incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible comprehenſibly manifeſteth himſelfe; in place higheſt, in ſubſtance not ſubiect to any corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or change, for it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all motion, and ſolid turneth not; in quantitie greateſt, for if one Starre, one Spheare bee ſo vaſt, how vaſt, how great muſt thoſe bounds bee which doth them all containe? In
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:177847:48"/>qualitie pureſt, Heauen here is all but a Sunne, or the Sunne all but a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, this is the onely and true <hi>Olympe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If to earthlings the foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoole of God ſeemeth ſo pleaſant, of what worth (if they could ſee) would they hold his Throne? And if the Throne bee ſo wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, what is the ſight of him for whom and by whom this <hi>All</hi> was created? Of whoſe glory to behold the thouſand thouſand part, the moſt pure intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are fully content, and with wonder and delight
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:177847:49"/>ſtand amazed; for the beauty of his light and the light of his beautie is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible.</p>
            <p>Here doth that earneſt appetite of the vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding pauſe it ſelfe, not ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to know any more, for it ſeeth before it in the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the diuine eſſence (a mirror in the which not I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages or ſhadows, but the true and perfect eſſence of all that is, is moſt viuely and perfectly ſeen) all that can be knowne, or vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood.</p>
            <p>Here is the will ſtayed,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:177847:49"/>louing that Soueraigne Good in whoſe fruition all good conſiſteth, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which can be none.</p>
            <p>Here is a bleſſed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, euery one reioycing in another and filled with ioy of themſelues, the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of one is the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of the whole, as the happines of the whole is the happineſſe of euery one: and as the company is innumerable, the ioy of each one is incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</p>
            <p>No ſilly Mortall confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned on that piece of earth,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:177847:50"/>who hath neuer ſeene but ſorrow, can rightly thinke of, or bee capable to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the happineſſe of this place.</p>
            <p>So many feathers moue not on Birds, ſo many Birds cleaue not the Ayre, ſo many leaues tremble not on Trees, ſo many Trees grow not in the wilde Forreſts, ſo many waues turne not in the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean,</hi> ſo many Sands bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not thoſe waues; as this Triumphing Court hath varietie of delights, and neuer loathſome plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:177847:50"/>
            <p>Ambition, Diſdaine, Malice, Ignorance, Error, Difference of opinions, doe not enter this place, reſembling the foggie miſts which couer thoſe liſts of ſublunary things.</p>
            <p>Here is Youth without Age, Strength without Weakeneſſe, Ioy without Sorrow, Light without Darkeneſſe, Life <hi>Without</hi> End, Ages doe neuer here expire, Time did neuer enter.</p>
            <p>All pleaſure paragon'd with what is here, is griefe, all Mirth mourning, all
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:177847:51"/>Beauty deformitie, heere one dayes abiding is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the continuing in the moſt Fortunate eſtate of the Earth many yeeres, and ſufficient to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile the extremeſt Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Life.</p>
            <p>Amongſt all the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the great Creator, not one appeareth to bee more ſtrange (replied I) then that the dead ſhould ariſe, Nature deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a regreſſe from priuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to a habit.</p>
            <p>Wonders (ſaid hee) in a wonderfull cauſe are no
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:177847:51"/>wonders, the Author of Nature is not thralled to the Lawes of Nature, but worketh with them or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary as it pleaſeth him, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whom nothing peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth.</p>
            <p>This world is as a Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, in which the ſmall things (though hid) are nothing leſſe kept then the great. To him who in an inſtant brought all this <hi>All</hi> from nought, to bring againe in an inſtant any thing that euer was in it to what it was once, ſhould not be thought impoſſible: Where the power is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:177847:52"/>limitation, the worke hath no other limitation then the workers Will; Reaſon her ſelfe finds it more poſſible for infinite power to deliuer from it ſelfe a finit World, and reſtore any thing in this world to what it was firſt, though decayed and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, then for a finit man, to change the forme of matter made to his hand.</p>
            <p>The power of God ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer brought to knowledge all that it can, for then were his infinit power bounded and finite.</p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:177847:52"/>
            <p>That time doth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach in which the dead ſhall liue, and the liuing bee changed, and of all actions the guerdon is at hand; then ſhall there bee an End without an End, Time ſhall finiſh, and Place bee altered, and another World of an age Eternall and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeable ſhall ariſe: With the which (mee thought) hee vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and I did all aſtoniſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
